New England Canal Ledgers and Charlestown Ledgers MS145
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
New England Canal Ledgers and Charlestown Ledgers
1800 -- 1864
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
MS145
2.3 Linear Feet
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into five series by subject matter and contain 11 ledgers, mostly from the early to mid- nineteenth century. The five series are: Middlesex Canal, Ledgers, 1808-1846; Union Canal, Ledgers, 1850-1851; Bow Canal, Ledgers, 1809-1853; Charlestown Records, Ledgers, ca. 1800's; Miscellaneous, Ledgers, 1827-1863.
Custodial History
The material was found together and uncatalogued in the stacks in the summer of 2007. They are of unknown provenance.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains a number of nineteenth-century ledgers. Most ledgers cover the activities of various canals in the northeastern United States. Two ledgers cover events of Charlestown, Massachusetts. One of those consists of handwritten summaries and citations of historical records from 1628-1641. Also noteworthy are ledgers listing the contents of ships traveling the Middlesex Canal.
The Middlesex Canal, built between 1793 and 1803, was an important transportation system in Massachusetts during the first half of the nineteenth century. Ceasing operation in 1853, the canal was a central part of the industrial, commercial and economic landscape. The Bow Canal, begun in New Hampshire in 1812, was also a main transportation route for the New England area. It stretched from Boston, Massachusetts to Manchester, New Hampshire. The Union Canal of Pennsylvania was an attempt to unify the economic ventures of the state via a principal travel route. It is one of the oldest existing transportation tunnels in the United States and was officially completed in 1828 by Canvass White, one of the chief engineers of the Erie Canal. Charlestown, Massachusetts, was first established on Shawmut Peninsula, just north of Boston, around 1629.
Middlesex Canal; Union Canal; Charlestown; Bow Canal; Greater Boston history
- Middlesex Canal, Ledgers, 1808 -- 1855; MS145.001; 1.75 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains ledgers that cover the activities of the Middlesex Canal in Massachusetts. Dates range from the early to mid- 19th century. Most of the material describes the expenditures of the canal as well as the contents of various shipments traveling the canal.
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged by ledger's subject matter.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Shipments on board outward-bound Middlesex Canal-Boats, Charlestown, 1808 -- 1810; MS145.001.001.00001 (Box MS145 Shared 1)
  - Account of Expenditures on Middlesex Canal, 1825 -- 1855; MS145.001.002.00001 (Box MS145 Shared 2)
  - Ledger, Middlesex Canal, 1835 -- 1846; MS145.001.002.00002 (Box MS145 Shared 2)
- Union Canal, Ledgers, 1850 -- 1851; MS145.002; 1.75 Linear Feet
  This series contains ledgers that cover the activities of the Union Canal of Pennsylvania. The dates range from 1850-1851. The bulk of the material covers the expenditures and accounts of the canal.
  The series is arranged based on the subject matter of the ledgers.
  - Union Canal Book, Moors Falls, BF Garvin Collector, 1851; MS145.002.001.00004 (Box MS145 Shared 1)
  - Union L and Canal Co., 1850; MS145.002.002.00004 (Box MS145 Shared 2)
- Bow Canal, Ledgers, 1809 -- 1853; MS145.003; 1.75 Linear Feet
  This series contains ledgers that detail the activities of the Bow Canal in New Hampshire. The dates range from 1809-1853. Most of the material lists the accounts and expenditures of the canal.
  - Copy Bills viz Bow Canal, 1809 -- 1812; MS145.003.001.00003 (Box MS145 Shared 1)
  - Bow Canal, 1825 -- 1853; MS145.003.002.00003 (Box MS145 Shared 2)
- Charlestown Records, Ledgers, 1800 -- 1846; 1833 -- 1846; MS145.004; 0.55 Linear Feet
  This series covers the events and history of Charlestown, Massachusetts. The dates are primarily from the 1800's, but a bulk of the material covers the early history of Charlestown. Most of the other material is from 1833-1846.
  - Charlestown Records, 1800; MS145.004.003.00002 (Box MS145 Shared 3)
  - Journal, Charlestown, 1835 -- 1846; MS145.004.003.00003 (Box MS145 Shared 3)
- Miscellaneous, Ledgers, 1827 -- 1864; MS145.005; 1.1 Linear Feet
  This series contains a few miscellaneous ledgers. The dates range from 1827-1863. Most detail expenditures and accounts relating to business matters. Some of the subject matter is unclear.
  - Cash Blotter, 1863-04 -- 1864; MS145.005.001.00002 (Box MS145 Shared 1)
  - Daybook, James Goddard Boston, 1827 -- 1836; MS145.005.003.00001 (Box MS145 Shared 3)